Guide to the Office of Public Affairs and Government Relations Reference Collection, 1939-1998
Duke University. University Archives
Office of Public Affairs and Government Relations Reference collection 1939-1998
Duke University. University Archives
0.5 linear feet Extent: 300 Items
The Office of Public Affairs and Government Relations Reference Collection contains files of memoranda, clippings, publications, and reports relating to the Office of Public Affairs and Government Relations and its predecessors. This collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research.
UA.01.11.0044
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Office of Public Affairs and Government Relations Reference Collection was compiled by University Archives staff from a variety of sources.
Historical Note
Around January of 1922, Henry Belk, Class of 1923, was named director of the Trinity College News Service. Apparently Belk was the College's first staff member hired for a public relations position. For 1927/28, the Bulletin of the University lists Albert Alexander Wilkinson, Class of 1927, as Director of Publicity. In 1935, the news service became part of the Department of Public Relations and Alumni Affairs which was directed by Henry R. Dwire. Wilkinson managed the News Service until 1945. The Bureau of Public Information succeeded the News Service in 1947/48. In 1948, Charles E. Jordan was named Vice President in the Division of Public Relations; he served in that capacity until 1966. In 1956, Clarence Whitfield became director of the Bureau of Public Information reporting to Jordan. The office was responsible for the University's news, radio, and television publicity. Personnel included a news director, a radio-TV director, and several writers. The Office of Information Services succeeded the Bureau in 1963/64. A 1963 report by the Barton Gillet Company titled "Analysis and appraisal of communications, Duke University" probably played a role in the reorganization of the University's strategies in this area. Now (2010), the Office of Public Affairs and Government Relations coordinates and manages communications strategies with the university's many audiences. It includes the offices responsible for federal, state and local government relations, local community affairs, campus news and communications and audiovisual services: Office of News and Communication; University Photography; Federal Relations; Office of Community Affairs; Government Relations. The Duke Medicine Office of News and Communications handles this function for the Duke University Medical Center.
Collection Overview
The collection includes newsletters, brochures, memoranda, clippings, statistics, reports, forms, printed matter, and other material concerning the University's public image and its management. The bulk dates are the 1960s to the 1990s. Among the items are blank reporting forms sent to faculty and staff to submit information for publicity; "Leads and Angles, Slants and Features: a handbook prepared for newspaper, magazine, and feature writers visiting Duke University," (April 1939); "Whom, Me?" a complication of national publicity following Professor A.C. Jordan's comments about Americans' poor grammar (1966); a series of publicity cards and statistics sheets, circa 1971, about the University and its various attractions including the Chapel, Gardens, Medical Center, and Art Museum; and "Duke Information Places Outside the Library Systems", a pamphlet apparently produced by the East Campus Library staff in 1980. Subjects include news staff assignments and facts and statistics about the University. In December of 1972, the News Service's director, Don Seaver, asked his staff to contribute items to a "Duke Facts" binder notebook. This binder included statistics, brief write-ups of the University and selected departments, class profiles, brochures, lists of several kinds, and other sorts of information. The binder was kept updated through the early 1980s. It is now stored in two file folders.
Subject Headings
Duke University. Office of News and Communications; Duke University -- Public relations
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, 1939-1998, (1 box)
  - Leads and Angles, Slants and Features, April 1939 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda, 1960-1968, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Bureau of Public Information, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Reporting forms, 1963-1975 (Box 1)
  - Noteworthy facts about Duke University, November, 1964 (Box 1)
  - News release, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Duke personnel holding offices in national organizations, ca. 1966 (Box 1)
  - Office of Information Services: Duke in the News [newsletter], 1965-1969 (Box 1)
  - Whom, me? 1967 [A.C. Jordan grammar story] (Box 1)
  - Publicity cards, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - Dateline Duke [newsletter], 1970 (Box 1)
  - Office of Information Services, memorandum, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Duke News Service Duke Facts binder (2 folders), 1972- (Box 1)
  - Duke News Service memos and flyers, ca. 1977-1992 (Box 1)
  - Duke Information Places, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Duke News Service Duke at a Glance [brochure], 1981-2001 (inc.) (Box 1)
  - Duke News Service Duke in the News [newsletter], 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Duke Government Report [newsletter], 1992 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1964-1998 (Box 1)
  - Duke and Durham Strategies for Initiating Community Development Projects: A Walltown Case Study / Lydia Faulkner, April 1994 (Box 1)
  - An Embattled Community: The West End of Durham / Katherine J. Richardson, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Durham and Duke: Duke University’s Estimated Total Annual Economic Impact on the City and County of Durham, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Advertisements, undated [after 1924] (Box 1)